Finding Aid for William L. Clements Papers 1920-1933
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William L. Clements papers 1920-1933
Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.
3 linear ft. and 1 oversize folder
Bay City, Michigan, industrialist, Republican member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, 1909-1933, and founder of the William L. Clements Library. University and regental files concerning selection of university presidents and other university affairs; and photographs.
861088;Aa;2;UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The files were transferred from the William L. Clements Library (donor no. 1333 ) in 1977.
The collection is open for research.
William L. Clements, born April 1, 1861, was educated at the University of Michigan then went to work as an engineer with the Industrial Works in Bay City, Michigan. He gradually worked his way up in the company, being promoted to the position of superintendent and manager, and then in 1898, to the office of president.
Clements was elected to the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan in 1909 and served until 1933. He was also founder of the William L. Clements Library of early Americana at the university and donated much of the collection as well as the building in which it was to be housed. He died November 6, 1934.
The collection consists of regental papers arranged alphabetically by correspondent. There is also a smaller series of photographic portraits. Clements' correspondents include University of Michigan presidents, administrators, faculty, as well as other members of the board of regents.
Subjects:
Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Women's League.; William L. Clements Library.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Clements, Jessie Young.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.
Contributors:
Beal, Junius Emery, 1860-1942.; Bulkley, Harry C. (Harry Conant), b. 1870.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955.; Christian, David Palmer, 1885-1947.; Cram, Esther Marsh.; Gore, Victor M.; Hanchett, Benjamin Sawtell, 1868-1933.; Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; Robbins, Frank Egleston, 1884-; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Shorts, Robert Perry, 1879-; Sink, Charles Albert, 1879-1972.; Smith, Ira Melville, 1885-1977.; Smith, Richard Root, 1869-1940.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.; Watkins, Herbert Gale, 1889-1967.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence files, 1920-1933
  - "A" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association (Box 1)
  - Beal, Junius E. (Box 1)
  - Bishop, William Warner, 1925-1927 (Box 1)
  - Board in Control of Athletics (F.H. Yost) (Box 1)
  - Bulkley, Harry C. (Box 1)
  - Burton, Marion L., 1921-1924 (Box 1)
  - Burton, Marion L. (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - "C" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Chase, Harry Woodburn (Box 1)
  - Chi Psi Fraternity (Box 1)
  - Christian, Palmer (Box 1)
  - Clements, William L (Travel expenditures) (Box 1)
  - Cram, Mrs. Esther Marsh (Box 1)
  - "D" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - "E" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Effinger, John R. (Box 1)
  - "F" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - "G" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Gore, Victor M. (Box 1)
  - Greve, Robert H. (Box 1)
  - "H" miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Hanchett, Benjamin S. (Box 1)
  - Hubbard, Lucius L. (Box 1)
  - Hutchins, Harry B. (Box 1)
  - "J" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - "L" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Little, Clarence C. (Box 2)
  - Lorch, Emil (Box 2)
  - "M" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Michigan Alumnus (Box 2)
  - Michigan League (Box 2)
  - Michigan Union (Box 2)
  - Murfin, James O. (Box 2)
  - "N" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - "O" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Pardon, E. C., 1923-1933 (Box 2)
  - "R" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Regent's file (miscellaneous notes, reports, etc.) (Box 2)
  - Robbins, Frank E. (Box 2)
  - Ruthven, Alexander G. (Box 2)
  - "S" miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Sawyer, Walter H. (Box 2)
  - Shorts, R. Perry (Box 2)
  - Sink, Charles A. (Box 2)
  - Smith, Ira, M (Box 2)
  - Smith, Richard R. (Box 2)
  - Smith, Shirley W., 1924-1934 (Box 3)
  - Stone, Ralph (Box 3)
  - "T" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - University File (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Club (Box 3)
  - "W" miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Watkins, Herbert (Box 3)
  - "Y" miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Portrait and portrait of wife Jessie Young Clements (Box 3)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)